A Finding Aid to the Chakaia Booker Papers, 1981-2018, bulk 1994-2010, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Chakaia Booker papers
1981-2018
bulk 1994-2010
Archives of American Art
Booker, Chakaia, 1953-
AAA.bookchak
Archival Resource Key
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of African American sculptor Chakaia Booker measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1981 to 2018 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1994 to 2010. The collection consists primarily of printed material, but also includes selected correspondence and professional files, including a portfolio.
Biographical / Historical
Chakaia Booker (1953- ) is an African American sculptor in New York, New York. In an artist's statement, Booker refers to herself as a "narrative environmental sculptor." She is known for large-scale sculptures incorporating recycled rubber tires and stainless steel. Booker's works are included in more than 40 public collections and have been exhibited across the United States and internationally. She has also served on the boards of International Sculpture Center and Socrates Sculpture Park.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1995-2013 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Professional Files, 1999-circa 2001 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1981-2018 (2.2 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Scope and Contents
The papers of African American sculptor Chakaia Booker measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1981 to 2018 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1994 to 2010. The collection consists primarily of printed material, including exhibition announcements; exhibition and auction catalogs; magazines; and newspapers. Also included are three folders of correspondence, including selected correspondence from artist Jack Whitten, and professional files, which includes a portfolio of Booker's work.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2018 by Chakaia Booker as part of the Archives' African American Collecting Initiative funded by the Henry Luce Foundation.
Women artists; African American artists; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; African American sculptors; Women sculptors; Whitten, Jack, 1939-2018
- Correspondence, 1995-2013; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence with museums, thank you letters Chakaia Booker received from students after a visit to the Rosa Park School, and a note and exhibition announcements from painter Jack Whitten.
  - Museums, 2001-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence and accompanying printed material from Cedarhurst Center for the Arts, the Akron Art Museum, and the DeCordova Museum and Sculpture Park.
  - Student Thank You Letters, Rosa Parks School, 2012-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jack Whitten, 1995-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes announcements for exhibitions of Whitten's work.
- Professional Files, 1999-circa 2001; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Professional files include a resume and artist statement, likely printed to accompany exhibitions, as well as a portfolio (removed from a binder) containing photographs, slides, and artist statements regarding her work. Booker distributed this portfolio to galleries and museums prior to being represented by Marlborough Gallery.
  - Chakaia Booker Resume and Artist Statement, 1999-circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Artist statement printed for Booker's work Industrial Subliminal-I-zation at Laumier Sculpture Park.
  - Portfolio, Removed from Binder, circa 1990s-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portfolio, Removed from Binder, circa 1990s-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, 1981-2018; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Printed material includes auction catalogs; announcements, invitations, and catalogs for exhibitions of Chakaia Booker's work; magazines; newsletters; newspapers; and reports from arts institutions.
  - Auction Catalogs, 1997; 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Calendar, Program, and Map, Garment District Arts Festival, 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cedarhurst Activity Book, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Event Calendars and Programs, 1981; 1994-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 1993-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1984-20018; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Solo Exhibitions, 2001-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Solo Exhibitions, 2009-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, 1999-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-9)
  - Oversize Magazines, 1998-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, Art in America, 1997-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Magazines, ARTnews, 1998-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Magazines, Sculpture, 1998-206; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Magazines, Time Out New York, 1996-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Magazines, Women in the Arts, 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters, 1994-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Oversize Newspapers, 1999-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Postcard, Photograph of Booker's Sculpture A Moment in Time (2004), Storm King Art Center, circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reports, Arts Institutions, 1999-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Includes reports for McNay Art Museum, Cedarhurst Center for the Arts, and Abington Art Center.